A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Multiple numbers
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by gift, purchase and deposit.
Scope and Content Information
This guide covers accessions #38-1 through #3675 (with occasional higher numbers) and includes information on approximately one-third of the collections in Special Collections.
Contents List
- Adams-Yates Ledgers 1872-1907, 1 item.
  An appraisal of the goods owned by Mary Yates at the times of her death (1907), as well as records of her transactions. 38-87
- Albemarle County Marriage Bonds 1786-1795, 1 item.
  As compiled by Mrs. Evelyn B. Wyllie. #3377
- Edwin Anderson Alderman Papers 1881-1950, 83 feet.
  Personal papers of Edwin Anderson Alderman, the first president of the University of Virginia. Topics include: the education of women in Virginia, and a speech entitled "Higher Education of Virginia Women (July 7, 1910). Correspondents include his wife, mother, daughter-in-law, Nancy Astor, Mary Barksdale, Anna Barringer, Elizabeth Bryce (viscountess), Lilian Dabney, Daughters of the American Revolution, Ethel Roosevelt Derby, and numerous others. #1001
- Allen Family Papers ca. 1825-1953, ca. 70 items.
  Personal letters of this Botetourt County family including correspondence of Mary Allen. #9780
- Elizabeth Barbour Ambler Papers 1748-1928, 3 boxes.
  Business and personal papers of three generations of Amblers: John, John Jacquelin and John Jacquelin, Jr., who owned property in Jamestown and estates in Amherst and Orange counties. Correspondents include Elizabeth Ambler (pre-1800), Catherine Ambler, Mrs. F. T. Barbour, Laura Ambler, and numerous others. Touches on education of children, plantation life, and family news. #1921
- Ambler Family Papers 1829-1834
  Personal papers of John Jacquelin Ambler (1801-1854) of Amherst County, Virginia and his father-in-law Philip Pendleton Barbour (1783-1841) of Orange County, Virginia, lawyer, politician, and jurist. Personal correspondents of J. J. Ambler and his wife Elizabeth Barbour Ambler include his parents, John Ambler and Catherine Bush Ambler, as well as Mrs. Ambler's sister, Philippa, and her mother, Mrs. Philip Pendleton Barbour. #38-77
- American Association of University Women Papers 1923-1975, ca. 85 items.
  Membership rosters, minutes, treasurer's reports, check registers, annual budgets and scrapbooks of the Charlottesville Chapter of the American Association of University Women. #6305-d
- Amole Family Papers 1826-1892, ca. 7 items.
  Papers of this Lexington family include two letters, 1865, from the "Taley" to Sallie Amole discussing their wedding plans. Of interest is a page from the family Bible and a catalogue from the State Female Normal School in Farmville, signed by Anna B. Johnson #9028
- Anderson Family Papers
  Collection (largely unprocessed) consisting of the personal, legal, and business correspondence of Francis Thomas Anderson, lawyer, legislator, judge and rector of Washington and Lee University; and his son William Alexander Anderson, lawyer, attorney general of Virginia and later rector of W & L. Highlights are the social life of Rockbridge County (1900-1930), the drawings of Ellen Graham Anderson, the Mount Vernon Ladies Association, and the United Daughters of the Confederacy. #38-96
- Anderson Family Papers 1950's
  Additional papers of the Lexington, Virginia family which primarily are the drawings by Ellen Graham Anderson of contemporary literary and dramatic figures. Also the correspondence of Ellen Graham Anderson with Judith Anderson and Mrs. Charles McCulloch. #38-96-f, -g.
- Ellen Graham Anderson 1963, 1 volume.
  Twenty-seven page typescript with autograph corrections of The Four Anderson Brothers of Walnut Hill, Fincastle, Virginia by Ellen Graham Anderson. #38-96-h
- W. D. Anthony Papers 1899-1953, 1 item.
  A collection of the poetry of W. D. Anthony, written ca. 1899-1953. Included is Battle Hymn of the Women written for the West Virginia suffrage campaign in 1916. #8844
- Argosy Collection 1795-1893, 103 items.
  Primarily letters and papers of Revolutionary and nineteenth century statesmen. A letter of interest is Benjamin Leigh (Virginia Senator) to Mrs. Frances Bland Coalter, March 26, 1813, dismissing her from her housekeeping duties because of his impending marriage and that she must keep his engagement a secret. #38-461
- Lady Nancy Astor May 10, 1922, 1 item.
  Lady Nancy Astor to Mrs. Charles Talbott, speaking of love for various things such as people and Virginia. #3358
- Myrta Lockett Avary Collection 1920's-1930's, ca. 15 items.
  A small collection of book reviews, magazine articles, etc., by Mrs. Myrta Lockett Avary of Atlanta, Georgia, author of Civil War and Reconstruction studies. #601
- Alice Aylett 1886, 1 certificate
  Certificate of proficiency in geometry, awarded to Alice Aylett by the Richmond Seminary, dated 18 June 1886, at Richmond, Virginia #38-321
- Barbour Family Papers 1793-1941, ca. 2275 items.
  Financial and legal papers of James Barbour of "Barboursville," Orange County and his descendants. Included is a significant amount of female correspondence generated by Caroline Homassel Ellis and other women. #1486
- Mary Barclay n.d., 1 volume.
  A manuscript of recipes for cooking, belonging to Mary Barclay. It is undated, but probably of the latter part of the nineteenth century (ca. 1870). #38-568
- Janie Porter Barrett Day Nursery Papers 1943-1948, ca. 75 items.
  This nursery was established for black children in Charlottesville, Virginia whose mothers had to work outside the home. Included in the papers are the constitution of the organization, financial records, a minute book of all the meetings and daily activities, an article entitled Children of Mothers who Work, as well as correspondence. The day nursery was constantly struggling to survive as evidenced by the correspondence from welfare and government agencies. #3283
- Barrett Assorted Authors 19th and 20th centuries, ca. 350 items.
  A collection of assorted authors' letters or other miscellany. Authors or writers mentioned: Alexandria, Queen Consort of Edward VII; Jane Cunningham Croly; May Abigail Dodge; Mary Katherine Field; Caroline Howard Gilman; Godey's Lady Book; Julia Ward Howe; Isabella Batchelder James; Carolina Kirkland; Mary Livermore; Harriet Lothrop; Julia Marlowe; Catherine Sedgwick; Lydia Sigourney; Ann Stephens; Marie Hansen Taylor; Mary Terhune; Celia Thaxter; Victoria, Queen of Great Britain; Jeanette Walworth; and Ella Wheeler Wilcox. #2587
- Barringer Family Papers 1828-1963, 2,830 items.
  Primarily the personal papers of Paul Brandon Barringer, professor of medicine and chairman of the faculty of the University of Virginia, and a founder of the University's Hospital. Material in regards to women is slight but does include some information on Anna Barringer, his daughter, including her "Memoirs of Dr. Paul Brandon Barringer", teaching and fine arts diplomas from Columbia University (June, 1914), as well as Eugenia Barringer's diploma from Hollins College (June 1915). Included are photocopies of letters between Stonewall Jackson and his wife, Mary Anna Morrison. #2588
- Barringer Family Papers
  An addition to the collection is Mrs. Barringer's Civil War diary in which she makes comments on both the war and home. #2588-f
- Eliot Fitch Bartlett Papers 1949-1967, 22 items.
  Bartlett corresponds with various government officials regarding matters of current political interest. Correspondents include Margaret Mary Heckler, congress woman, and June A. Willenz, executive director, American veterans committee. #3630-f.
- Eliot Fitch Bartlett Papers 1937-1973, ca. 35 items.
  Barlett corresponds with senators and congressmen on current issues. Correspondents include Clare Booth Luce and Margaret Mary Heckler. #3630-k through -n
- Eliot Fitch Bartlett Papers 1932-1937, 1967, 1978, 7 items.
  The papers contain a biographical note on Emma (Garrison) Jones (1833-1896). #3630-o-p.
- Baugh Family Papers 1756-1942, ca. 10,000 items.
  Collection (largely unprocessed) containing material relating to Leonidas Baugh and his family in Abingdon, Virginia. There is some correspondence generated by women, of note are the letters between Leonidas Baugh and his wife during the Civil War, and school exercises of their daughters Minnie and Ida. #2833
- Baylor Family Papers 1653-1915, ca. 2000 items.
  The papers of several generations of the Baylor family of "Newmarket", Caroline County, Virginia, consisting of financial and legal papers, ledgers, genealogical material, and correspondence. The papers contain substantial material relating to the Revolutionary War. Items of interest include the will of Frances Baylor (1815), Eliza Baylor to Louisa Upshaw, September 13, 1830, describing a parade in Richmond celebrating the French victory over the Bay of Algiers, Frances Baylor to Louisa Upshaw, July 18, 1813, discusses visitors at "Newmarket", fever in Essex County, and that many people are fleeing Richmond due to the British, Isabella Hunter to Mrs. John Baylor, January 28, 1757, concerning the death of her husband, a groom in Colonel Baylor's stables, and more correspondence concerning women. #2257
- Jane Beale 1850-1862, 1 item.
  Manuscript journal, 1850-1862 of Mrs. Jane Beale of Fredericksburg, Virginia. The original as of 1984, was on display at the Fredericksburg and Spotsylvania National Military Park. She is very concerned with war news and writes of nearby battles. #Microfilm M-3288
- Blake Family Papers 1842-1932, 166 items.
  Correspondence and business papers of the itinerant dentist Dr. John T. Blake of Greenbrier County, West Virginia. The business and legal papers of the Blake family contain accounts and tax receipts of Dr. Blake, his mother Rhoda Blake, and his sister, Mary E. (Blake) Lemmnons. The school essays of Mary Blake, a memorandum book of Esther Blake, and an unidentified photograph are found in the miscellaneous folder. #8975
- Ann Beattie Interview 1987, 1 item.
  Electrostatic copy, original in possession of James Dell. Copy of a transcript of an interview with Beattie conducted by James Dell for a high school course. Beattie discusses her views on writing, critics, other authors, the influence of popular music on her work and her recent venture into non-fiction. #10414-n
- Ann Beattie Letter February 13 n.y., 1 item.
  To Robie [McCauley], Beattie writes thanking McCauley for a book he has sent and mentioning that she is going to hear Robert Stone read that night. #10414-k.
- Ann Beattie Papers 1985-1986, 10 items.
  In a series of letters, Beattie receives requests from representatives of various publishing companies for advance reviews of unpublished novels. Also included in the collection is a copy of a piece of work entitled North Garden. #10414-j
- Bell Family Papers ca. 1790-1880, ca. 200 items.
  Business and legal papers of the Augusta County, Virginia family including females. Also included is a document noting a public sale of a superannuated female slave to be cared for by the lowest bidder. #Microfilm M-1313. 6688.
- Berkeley Family Papers 1653-1930, ca. 20,000 items.
  Personal, business and legal papers of this family of Barn Elms, Middlesex County, Aldie, Loudoun County, and Albemarle County, Virginia. References in early wills to wives, daughters concerning property and marriage settlements. Collection does not have a detailed guide. #38-113
- Elizabeth Crew (Ambler) Blackford Collection 1780-1966, 5 items.
  Electrostatic copies of three letters from Betsy Ambler, daughter of the Treasurer of Virginia, to Mildrid Stith describing the flight of her family and other public officials from Richmond to Charlottesville, thus eluding the pursuit of Tarleton's army. See also the related accessions 6723 and 7661. #6403-i.
- Launcelot Minor Blackford Papers 1849-1860, 150 items.
  Primarily the education papers of L. M. Blackford at the University of Virginia; however, there is correspondence from Ambler M. Blackford to his mother, Nannie Ambler. #38-204
- Blackwell Family Papers ca. 1840-1848, 15 items.
  Personal correspondence of Elizabeth Blackwell and family members of Fauquier County, Virginia. Some mention of slaves such as a letter of June 22, n.y., from Octavia mentioning that a slave tried to get away in Cincinnati as they were going to Missouri, and a letter of June 30, n.y., from Sarah T. Buckner who wants to collect on a loan so that she can buy a slave's husband and send them both west. Letters from the family members who moved to Missouri provide insights into the emotional and physical hardships involved in such immigration. #38-143-b
- John Blake Family Papers 1842-1932, 166 items.
  The papers contain correspondence, business and legal papers of Blake, itinerant, dentist from Greenbrier County [West] Virginia. There are accounts and tax receipts of Blake, his mother Rhoda and sister Mary E. Lemmons, some of it pertaining to dentistry. Correspondence, chiefly with his family and his in-laws, the Dotsons of Fayette County, West Virginia, conveys family news and discusses his practice. Of interest is a letter reacting to John Brown's raid. #8975
- Elizabeth C. Blaetterman Letter June 30, 1860, 1 item.
  Elizabeth C. Blaetterman of Maysville, Kentucky, to "Victoria" in Virginia. Comments on how both male and female are teaching these days just for their board. Writes primarily of her freed servants (slaves) and how they are doing in their lives. Evidently, Mr. Blaetterman would purchase a slave with the intent of setting the slave free, but the freed slave would pay back Mr. Blaetterman his purchase price. It seems Mr. Blaetterman did this to keep slave families together. She regrets not doing more. #799
- Bledsoe Family Papers 1858-1908, n.d., ca. 60 items.
  Letters to Albert Taylor Bledsoe and Sophia Bledsoe Herrick, usually from prominent people. Correspondents include Margaret Preston, Cornelia Grinnan. Frances Hodgson Burnett, Anna B. Warner, Margaret Sangster, Ellen Glasgow, Frances Power Cobbe, Fanny D. Lowell, and Celia Thaxter. #3461
- Bledsoe Family Papers, Additional 1837-1951, 3 items.
  In a letter, 1951, Louise Herrick Wall writes Elizabeth D. Halladay concerning unfavorable comments about A. T. Bledsoe in Philip Alexander Bruce's History of the University of Virginia, and in an article by Edwin Mims. The collection includes a photograph of Sophia Childress Bledsoe. #3461-a
- Booker, Dabney and Perkins Family Papers 1850-1870, ca. 200 items.
  Miscellaneous collection concerning the above families of Albemarle County and Richmond, Virginia. Of interest is a set of letters to Mildred Perkins from her cousins in Bolton, Mississippi after the Civil War. Evidently the families had never met and were trying to establish contact after the War. One letter of particular note, Virginia McKay, January 2, 1870, writes "the last sensation was a female lecturer from the North, one of the strong minded, I suppose, she looked very masculine, her subject was phrenology, which she could not possible do justice to....we went through curiosity and are fully convinced that speaking public is not a woman's prerogative." (2317-d). Also of interest is a broadside for a "Grand Military Ball" to be held at Camp Carondelet, February 25, 1862, and a packet of letters to Mildred Perkins about love, marriage and life among young people before the Civil War (2317-e) #2317-d and 2317-e
- Booker Family Papers 1863-1879, 45 items.
  Booker family of Lynchburg, Virginia, primarily the miscellaneous papers of James M. Booker of Lynchburg. A letter dated November 7, 1872, to "Dear Pa" from Blanch, who is attending the Virginia Female Institute, writes of a woman who is being force fed because of her refusal to eat and also expresses her dismay that Grant was elected. Other items include letters from Mrs. Booker to Mr. Booker (October 12, 1873; April 3, 1876 and May 20, n.d.) concerning family and general news. #2481.
- Belle Boyd 1870-1914, 4 letters (photocopies)
  Four letters concerning impressions of the Confederate spy, Belle Boyd. #2582
- Mary Boyden Commonplace Book 1872, 1 item.
  Volume of poetry and essays, 1868-1872, presented to Henrietta Boyden by her mother, Mary Boyden, on July 23, 1872. Inscribed "Thoughts for weary hours' for my darling Henrietta." #3638
- Sarah Patton Boyle Papers ca. 1950-1970, ca. 12,000 items.
  Personal, legal, and business papers of this Charlottesville woman who was involved in school integration and other civil rights issues in central Virginia in the 1950's and 1960's. Correspondents include editors of women magazines, Marjory Cherry, Winifred Clapp, Mrs. Samuel L. Abbott, Jr., Peggy Collison, Mrs. Paul J. Furnas, June P. Guild, Ruth Haefner, Elly Haney, Mrs. Heslip M. Lee, Jane McClary, Janet Johnston, Narcissa D. Overstreet, and Susie Peace (Richmond Times Dispatch). Also included is correspondence with black leaders such as Ralph Abernathy and Martin Luther King. #8003, -a, -b
- Bradford Letters 1843-1852, 21 items.
  Majority of the letters are from Mary Bradford Thomas to William and Lucy Stuart, probably her sister and her husband, of Lewisburg, Greenbrier County, Virginia. Mary, as reflected in her letters, was pessimistic, and wrote much about the deaths of relatives and friends. #543
- James Brady Papers 1819-1859, 265 items.
  Correspondence, legal, and business papers of James Brady, merchant, of Scottsville, Virginia. A document of interest is a Copy of a Reply from a Married Lady to her Young Female Companion... written by a new bride to an unmarried female which details her wedding night and present state of marital happiness. (April, 1837). #38-597
- Rachel Bramham Collection 1852-1890, 27 items.
  Letters from various friends and relatives to Miss Rachel Bramham of Scottsville, Albemarle County, Virginia. Subjects include the Civil War, the death of several infants and children in the area, and the hanging of two men (Trayer and Wilson) in Staunton for murder (January 3, 1854) #3437
- Lawrence O'Bryan Branch Papers ca. 1840-1880, ca. 650 items.
  Personal, political, and military correspondence of the North Carolina citizen. There is correspondence between Branch and his wife. Microfilm 2296 (#10057)
- Robert S. Brooke Papers 1792-1927, 100 items.
  The collection consists chiefly of correspondence between Brooke and his wife, Margaret Lye Smith Brooke, written while he was serving in the General Assembly. Topics of interest include male views on childbirth and a copy of Betty Louden Berkeley's will (1866). #38-137
- Caroline Morril Brown 1910, 1 item.
  "War-time Memories by an Old Lady Who was Then Young," (electrostatic copy) by Caroline Morril Brown. Mrs. Brown was a governess for the Maury family of "Piedmont," Albemarle County, and she penned her memoirs of the Civil War in 1910. #2129-a
- Milton McIntyre Brown Letters 1916-1918, 9 items.
  Electrostatic copies, originals in possession of relative of Brown, a World War I soldier. Collection consists chiefly of the letters of Milton McIntyre Brown to various family members while he was in Belgium and France as a member of the 324th Field Artillery in the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I. Also included is a letter, June 10, 1916, from Mrs. Bruce Brown, New York City, to "My dearest boys" regarding the departure of two of her sons for overseas. #10719
- James Bruce Family Papers 1746, 1800-1900, 27 boxes
  The business, financial and personal papers of the Bruce family of "Berry Hill", Halifax County. There is much correspondence generated by women including: Elvira A. Bruce, Mary P. Govan, Eliza Bruce, Mildred H. Carrington, Mary Elizabeth A. Bruce. Mrs. A. A. Anderson, Mary Evelyn Anderson, Ann Green, Sally Bruce, Sally Brodnax, Catherine Carrington, Fanny Anderson etc. A strong ante-bellum, Civil and Reconstruction collection. #2692
- Brunswick County Papers 1811-1869, ca. 30 items.
  Documents and letters, some of which refer to the hiring and leasing of slaves. Also included is a December 11, 1824, letter apparently from a black woman in Petersburg, Virginia, who is writing in an attempt to gain some form of recompense for an ancestor, Ned Brandom, who served as a substitute in the Revolutionary War. Also included are documents concerning Elizabeth Rainey of Georgia. There are two letters to John Tucker of Smokey Ordinary, Virginia concerning the rent he owes her. There are 12 items relating to Mary Ann Tucker (of Georgia) who also rents land to John Tucker. Material refers to contracts, rents, land, and slaves. #3307,-a
- Bryan Family Papers 1770-1918, ca. 645 items.
  Correspondence of the Bryan, Tucker, and Randolph families. John Randolph of Roanoke and George St. Tucker are the two predominant correspondents, however, there is much written to and by women. Correspondents include Elizabeth Tucker Coalter Bryan, Mrs. Joseph Bryan, Frances Bland Coalter, and Judith Randolph. Also of interest is a letter (3400-b) Elizabeth Coalter Tucker Bryan to her husband, John Randolph Bryan, November 3, 1852, regarding illness of slaves presidential election returns and her efforts as household nurse dispensing quinine and lancing a finger. (3400) #3400-b and 3400
- Lucy Buck Diary 1862, 1 item.
  First section (1862) typescript) of the diary of Lucy R. Buck (1842-1918) of Front Royal, Virginia. A portion of the original manuscript diary is filed in the Buck Family papers (4932). Diary covers 1862-1863 and is concerned with local soldiers, politics and battles. Related material in accessions 704, 1091, 3064, 4932, 4938) (622). #4932, 622
- Richard Bayly Buck Papers 1861-1865, 218 items.
  Civil War letters to Richard B. Buck of the Warren Rifles, Virginia 17th Regiment, from various family members and friends. His mother Jane Buck writes to him, May 13, 1861, praying for any early end to the war and that no blood will be shed, but if so "that the calamity fall upon the heads of our enemy." In a letter, May 21, 1861, she wishes he would spend some time with the ladies," I do not like your being so long from under the influence of ladies society." Jane Buck's early letters clearly express her concern about her son's morals and the effect war and "bad company" may have on him. She writes to remember his God and prayers. However, as the war drags on, her letters change tone, but she always encourages her son to invoke the protection of God. Other items of interest are the letters of his cousins, Nell and Lucy Buck (of the above diary). Lucy's are very serious from the beginning, but Nell's are light-hearted, but as with Jany Buck's letters, her correspondence also grows more somber as the war progressed. These letters seem to reflect the mood of the South at the beginning of the War, that all this was going to be a great and heroic adventure, until it was obvious the war wasn't going to be over in a month. #3064
- Helen Claire Bullock 1862-1863, 1 item.
  Diary kept during 1862-1863. From Northern Virginia Helen wrote of the war and nearby troops. Her writings provide a good understanding of how the war affected a young woman. #8635.
- Lucy Wood Butler 1859-1863, 1 item.
  Letters and diary of Lucy Wood Butler of "Locust Hill", Albemarle County, Virginia, 1859-1863. Includes correspondence with her husband Woody Butler of Fernandina, Florida. She began a diary and wrote until 1863. She was concerned with war news, deaths and her husband's absence. Microfilm 234; (#2695).
- Cabell-Carrington Papers 1776-1852, ca. 1000 items.